A Guide to the Population Council records, Ford Foundation Projects, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 6 FA1293
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Tunisia Office collected press clippings, 1964-1975; 2; 2 Cubic Feet About 4.25 LGL size Hollinger Boxes
  The subseries is comprised of various newspaper clippings. Clippings generally regard family planning related subjects in Tunisia, l'Office National du Planning Familial et de la Population (National Office of Family Planning and Population) and its preceding organizations, political developments in the Tunisia Government, and family planning related subjects in countries outside of Tunisia.
  Press clippings in the first part of the subseries are grouped into files based upon the articles' dates of publication. These files contain clippings from mostly Tunisian newspapers that were published between 1969 and 1975. Press clippings in the second part of the subseries are grouped into files based upon the sources of the articles, such as French or American newspapers, and upon the content of the articles with subjects like education and public health represented.
  - Clippings: Articles, November 1971-December 1971 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    Includes file description note for the contents of all files named Clippings: Articles from the year 1971.
  - Clippings: Articles, October 1971 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Clippings: Articles, June 1971-September 1971 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - Clippings: Articles, May 1971 (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Clippings: Articles, April 1971 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Clippings: Articles, March 1971 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Clippings: Articles, January 1971-February 1971 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Clippings: Articles, 1972-1974 August (Box 20, Folder 228-242)
  - Clippings: Articles and General, 1974 September-1975 December (Box 21, Folder 243-251)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, December 1970 (Box 9, Folder 110)
    Related Materials
    Includes file description note for the contents of all files named Clippings: Coupures de journaux from the year 1970. All files with this title contain press clippings from Tunisian daily newspapers published in 1970.
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, October 1970-November 1970 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, July 1970-September 1970 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, May 1970-June 1970 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, March 1970-April 1970 (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, January 1970-February 1970 (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, October 1969-December 1969 (Box 9, Folder 116)
    Includes file desription note for the contents of all files named Clippings: Coupures de journaux from the year 1969. Files with this title contain press clippings from Tunisian daily newspapers published in 1969.
    Materials within this file primarily originate from December 1969. However, there is a group of undated press clippings and a clipping from October 1969 also included.
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, November 1969 (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, October 1969 (Box 9, Folder 118)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, September 1969 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, August 1969 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux, January 1969-July 1969 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Clippings: French newspapers and others, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Clippings: Coupures de la presse, VIII el Congres du Parti Socialiste Destourien, October 1971-Novermber 1971 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - Clippings: Coupures de la presse, VIII el Congres du Parti Socialiste Destourien, October 1971 (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - Clippings: Coupures de la presse, VIII el Congres du Parti Socialiste Destourien, October 1971 (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Clippings: Coupures de la presse, VIII el Congres du Parti Socialiste Destourien, October 1971 (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Clippings: Public health, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 127)
  - Clippings: General Tunisia Government policy, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - Clippings: American newspapers, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 129)
    File contains a photocopy of an article by John D. Rockefeller, 3rd that appeared in the Reader's Digest in October 1966. Titled "The Greatest Challenge of Our Time", it discusses the Population Council's efforts to promote family planning throughout the world as well as Rockefeller's visit to see the family planning program in Tunisia. Rockefeller served as the Chairman of the Population Council Board of Trustees at the time that this article was published.
  - Clippings: Employment, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 130)
  - Clippings: Family planning, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 131)
  - Clippings: Family welfare, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 132)
  - Clippings: Logement, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 133)
  - Clippings: General, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 134)
  - Clippings: Education, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 135)
  - Clippings: Coupures de journaux etrangers, VIII el Congres du Parti Socialiste Destourien, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 136)
  - Clippings: Tunisia Government budget, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 137)
  - Clippings: General, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 138)
  - Clippings: Family planning and other topics, 1964-1968 (Box 11, Folder 139)
    Original note on folder: Extras from scrapbook
    Contains file description notes that list the press clippings included within the file by year of publication.
  - Clippings: General, 1965-1972 (Box 11, Folder 140)
    File includes a copy of the publication "Science et vie".
- Ceylon Office files, 1960-1971, bulk 1967-1971; 3
  This subseries primarily concerns the administrative operations of the regional Population Council Office in Colombo, Ceylon (present day Sri Lanka). Nicholas H. Wright served as Population Council Resident Representative (also referred to as Resident Advisor) for the Ceylon Office from 1967 until the end of 1970. Correspondence, invoices, receipts, bank account statements, bills, and a limited number of ads document the business expenses Wright approved in relation to utility payments, equipment purchases, and supply imports for the Population Council Office at 33/7 De Fonseca Place, the residence bungalow at 15/7 Maitland Crescent, and the Family Planning Bureau office at 5 Bagatelle Road. Many files that contain these types of materials bear the name of the specific company or Ceylon Government Agency that issued or approved the particular services or products the files document. Others have titles that describe the specific material formats they contain such as bills or receipts. The subseries also includes a small group of personnel files for Secretary and Administrative Assistant Avril M. Jayawardene and other staff members, correspondence with Population Council and Ford Foundation officials in New York, and a collection of Population Council Board of Trustees and Executive Committee meeting agendas. These meeting agendas consist of more than just subject items and instead include descriptions and summaries of developments and plans within the organization. It appears that for every assembly of the Board of Trustees or Executive Committee, the Population Council may have distributed a meeting agenda copy to each of its regional offices.
  A smaller group of records documents the Ceylon Office's statistical work and collaborative family planning program efforts. Wright, his staff, and his partner organizations generally collected statistics to study the use of contraceptives within the Ceylon population, the availability and use of family planning services and clinics within the country, and the demographic background information of family planning acceptors. The subseries contains correspondence, reports, tables, sample surveys, and clinical forms that provide evidence of this work. Drafts and notes are housed with many of these reports and tables. The Population Council Office in Ceylon chiefly worked with the Ceylon Ministry of Health (MOH) and the Swedish International Development Authority (SIDA – present day Swedish International Development Cooperation Agency) on family planning projects. Several files contain materials that discuss how the SIDA-sponsored Swedish-Ceylon Family Planning Program helped the Population Council in establishing its regional office in the country. The MOH Department of Health Services took over the Sweden-Ceylon Family Planning Program in 1968 and established the Family Planning Bureau. With help from the Population Council and SIDA, the Bureau sought to advance the National Family Planning Programme in Ceylon. Various types of reports and correspondence regard the progress and activities of the Bureau and the Population Council's work with it. Materials originating from the years 1969-1970 that concern the Bureau discuss an increasing political opposition to family planning work in Ceylon.
  Staff dismissal letters in the personnel files indicate that in early 1971, the Population Council closed its regional office in Ceylon.
  - Ceylon Ministry of Health, 1968-1971 (Box 11, Folder 141)
  - Dr. Terence Perera, Assistant Director of Health, Maternal and Child Health, Family Planning Bureau, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 142)
  - Population Council correspondence with Director of Health Services, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 143)
  - Population Council, New York, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 144)
  - Population Council correspondence with principals in United States, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 145)
  - Population Council, New York, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 146)
  - Ford Foundation, New York, 1967-1969 (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - United States Agency for International Development, 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 148)
  - Grant File and Budget File: Interim reports, 1966-1970 (Box 12, Folder 149)
  - Grant File: Postpartum Family Planning Program Proposal, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 150)
  - Family Planning Bureau shared expenses with Swedish International Development Authority, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 151)
  - Sweden-Ceylon family planning program, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 152)
    In addition to containing documents regarding the Sweden-Ceylon Family Planning Program, the file also includes materials related to the Family Planning Bureau and the Swedish International Development Authority (SIDA). The Family Planning Bureau replaced the Sweden-Ceylon Family Planning Program when the Ceylon Ministry of Health Department of Health Services took over command of the organization in 1968, and SIDA supported both organizations in terms of advisory staff and financial resources.
  - Sweden-Ceylon family planning program, 1967-1970 (Box 12, Folder 153)
  - Ceylon Controller of Immigration and Emigration, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 154)
  - First National City Bank, New York, 1967-1969 (Box 12, Folder 155)
  - Ceylon Ministry of Planning and Economic Affairs, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 156)
  - Bank account, Dr. Nicholas H. Wright, 1967-1970 (Box 12, Folder 157)
  - Department of Exchange Control, Central Bank of Ceylon, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 158)
  - University of Ceylon Population Study, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 159)
    The contents of this file pertain to the same study as the one documented within the University of Ceylon Fertility Survey file, located in Box: 14, Folder: 178. The series creator appears to have used both titles to describe the research project.
  - Family Planning Bureau Evaluation Reports, 1-6, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 160)
    File contains same contents as the Family Planning Bureau Evaluation Reports, 1-6 file located in Box: 13, Folder: 170.
  - Ceylon family planning project reports, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 161)
  - Quarterly Reports on New Acceptors of Family Planning, 1968-1970 (Box 13, Folder 162)
  - Ceylon Department of Government, Electrical Undertakings: Electric bills, 1967-1970 (Box 13, Folder 163)
  - Ceylon Department of Government, Electrical Undertakings: Electric bills, 1967-1970 (Box 13, Folder 164)
  - Telephone, bungalow, 1968-1971 (Box 13, Folder 165)
  - Telephone, Population Council office and Family Planning Bureau, 1967-1971 (Box 13, Folder 166)
  - Population Council office landlord, M. B. Perera, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 167)
  - Bungalow landlord, R. D. Ponniah, 1967-1970 (Box 13, Folder 168)
  - Family Planning Bureau landlord, P.R. Thambiayah, 1968-1970 (Box 13, Folder 169)
  - Family Planning Bureau Evaluation Reports, 1-6, 1969-1970 (Box 13, Folder 170)
    File contains same contents as the Family Planning Bureau Evaluation Reports, 1-6 file found in Box: 12, Folder: 160.
  - Surveys of family planning acceptance, circa 1968-1969 (Box 13, Folder 171)
    An oversized item titled List of clinics, family planning clinics associated with the Family Planning Association of Ceylon, family planning clinics on estates, and municipal clinics has been removed from the file in order to be moved to a flat storage container. This item has been assigned the unique separation number 2017:FA1293:002.
  - International Postpartum Family Planning Program, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 172-173)
  - Ceylon Ministry of Health quarterly reports, 1968-1970 (Box 14, Folder 174)
  - Family planning service statistics, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 175)
  - Family planning service statistics, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 176)
  - Family planning clinic record forms, circa 1966-1968 (Box 14, Folder 177)
  - University of Ceylon Fertility Survey, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 178)
    The contents of this file pertain to the same study as the one documented within the University of Ceylon Population Study file, located in Box: 12, Folder: 159. The series creator appears to have used both titles to describe the research project.
  - Family planning service statistics feedback system, 1967-1969 (Box 14, Folder 179)
  - Superintendents of Health Services feedback report, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 180)
  - Air waybills, 1967-1969 (Box 14, Folder 181-182)
  - Air waybills, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 183)
  - Walker, Sons, and Co., Ltd.: Carrier air conditioners and geyser, 1967-1970 (Box 15, Folder 184)
  - I.A.C. (Singapore), 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 185)
  - H.W. Cave and Co., 1967-1970 (Box 15, Folder 186)
  - Volkswagen coach, Car Mart, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 187)
  - Colonial Motors Ltd.: Land rovers, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 188)
  - Collettes Ltd., 1967-1970 (Box 15, Folder 189)
  - Caxton Printing Works Ltd., 1968-1970 (Box 15, Folder 190)
  - E.B. Creasy and Co. Ltd., 1968-1969 (Box 15, Folder 191)
  - Brown and Co. Ltd. Engineers and Merchants: Typewriter and other office equipment repairs, 1967-1970 (Box 15, Folder 192)
  - Eastern Agencies (Singapore), Anglo-Thai Corporation Ltd., 1967-1970 (Box 15, Folder 193)
  - Items of office equipment and furniture ordered for office and bungalow, 1967-1970 (Box 16, Folder 194)
  - Ceylon population projections, 1968-1970 (Box 16, Folder 195)
  - Ceylon population projections, 1968-1970 (Box 16, Folder 196)
  - National and Grindlay's Bank Ltd.: Bank statements, January 1970-December 1970 (Box 16, Folder 197)
  - National and Grindlay's Bank Ltd.: Bank statements, August 1967-December 1969 (Box 16, Folder 198)
  - Population Council memos to Ceylon Ministry of Health, 1969-1970 (Box 16, Folder 199)
  - Population Council Board of Trustees: Agenda for meeting of October 16, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 200)
  - Population Council Executive Committee: Agenda for meeting of December 11, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 201)
  - Population Council Board of Trustees: Agenda for meeting of March 5, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 202)
  - Population Council Board of Trustees: Agenda for annual meeting of June 4, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 203)
  - Population Council Executive Committee: Agenda for meeting of September 17, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 204)
  - Population Council Board of Trustees: Agenda for meeting of December 10, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 205)
  - Population Council Board of Trustees: Agenda for annual meeting of April 2, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 206)
  - Correspondence with Ceylon Controller of Imports and Exports, 1967-1970 (Box 17, Folder 207)
  - Ceylon Principal Collector of Customs, 1967-1970 (Box 17, Folder 208)
  - A.M.S. Joachim personnel file, 1960-1971 (Box 17, Folder 209)
  - Avril M. Jayawardene personnel file, 1966-1971 (Box 17, Folder 210)
  - Staff salary receipts, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 211)
  - Staff salary receipts, 1967-1969 (Box 17, Folder 212)
  - Other staff members personnel file, 1967-1970 (Box 18, Folder 213)
  - Cash receipts: Petty cash, 1967-1971 (Box 18, Folder 214)
  - Credit invoices, 1967-1970 (Box 18, Folder 215)
  - Credit receipts, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 216)
  - Traveling claims: Evaluation Officers, medical statistics, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 217)
  - Registered letter counterfoils, 1967-1970 (Box 18, Folder 218)